Today's דף *daf* is ק"ה *Kuf Hey*, 105. We pick up on
the bottom third of ק"ד עמוד ב' *Kuf Dalet Amud Bet*, the
new פרק perek *perek*. We are now beginning the last פרק *perek*
of מסכת מנחות menachot *Masechet Menachot*, just a few days away from
finishing the מסכת *masechet*. All right, so here we go. הרי עלי
עישרון *Harei alai isaron*, if somebody takes upon himself a vow to
bring an עישרון *isaron*, which is the standard amount of flour for
a מנחה mincha *mincha*, so obviously in the context we understand that
means a מנחה mincha *mincha* of an עישרון *isaron*, then יביא אחד
*yavi echad*, so bring one עישרון *isaron*. I mean, that's pretty obvious,
but okay. עישרונות *Isaronot*, I accept upon myself a vow to bring
עישרונות *isaronot*, and again implicitly מנחה mincha, *mincha* of עישרונות *isaronot*, יביא
שניים *yavi shenayim*, you bring two, because that is the minimum, and
you can't obligate the person in more than the minimum of what
he means. פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי *Perashti ve-eini yodea ma perashti*,
when somebody comes to the rabbi and he says, or the כהנים
kohanim *kohanim* or whatever, and he says, you know, when I took
a vow, I said x עישרונות *isaronot*, a מנחה mincha *mincha* of
x עישרונות *isaronot*, but I don't remember what the x was. So
יביא ששים עישרון *yavi shishim isaron*, then bring a מנחה mincha, *mincha*
of sixty עישרון *isaron*, because we learned in the past that
more than sixty is not allowed, so the maximum is sixty. And
when you bring this, you basically say,
however much I vowed is for my vow, and the additional part,
if there is any additional, if it was less than sixty,
then
x is for my vow and 60 minus x is an additional
מנחה mincha *mincha*, a free-will מנחה mincha *mincha*. All right, whether how
you do that is it one big מנחה mincha. *mincha* in one
כלי kli *kli*, is it separate כלים keilim *keilim*, we'll see about
that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to some degree in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. But that's how you manage to cover your bases. הרי
עלי מנחה mincha *Harei alai mincha*, יביא איזו שירצה *yavi eizo she-yirtze*.
If somebody just says I accept upon myself a vow to bring
a מנחה mincha *mincha*, then he can bring any of the מנחות
menachot *menachot* that are mentioned in the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra: *Vayikra*,
because he did not specify which. So those are סולת soleth *solet*,
the simple flour and oil, מחבת machavat, *machavat*, מרחשת marcheshet, *marcheshet*, frying
pan, deep pan, and then the two types of מאפה תנור ma'afeh
tanur, *ma'afeh tanur*, which is חלות chalot, *challot* and רקיקים *rekikin*. So
since you didn't say which type, you can bring whichever one you
want. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר יביא מנחת סולת minchat soleth שהיא
מיוחדת meyuchedet, שבמנחות *Rabbi Yehuda omer yavi minchat solet she-hi meyuychedet she-be-menachot*.
No, you have to bring the one of flour because that is
distinctive,
designated somehow amongst the מנחות menachot. *menachot*, and we'll see what that
means in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. But that's assumed by default according
to him what you mean. מנחה Mincha. או מן המנחה
*Mincha o min hamincha*, if somebody says I obligate myself to bring
a מנחה Mincha *mincha* or from the types of מנחה Mincha *mincha*,
then יביא אחת *yavi achat*, bring one obviously. מנחות menachot או מן
המנחות *Menachot o min hamenachot*, if I obligate myself to bring מנחות
menachot, *menachot*, plural, or a type of מנחות Menachot, *menachot*, יביא שתיים
*yavi shtayim*, then bring two. And presumably they would have to be
of the same type, both מרחשת marcheshet *marcheshet* or מחבת machavat *machavat*
and so on, we'll see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
But because you used the plural, it means two. פירשתי ואיני יודע
איזה מהם פירשתי *Perashti ve-eini yodea eizeh mehem perashti*, I vowed to
bring a מנחה Mincha, *mincha* but I don't remember which of the
standard five. So יביא חמשתן *yavi chameshtan*, bring all five to play
it safe. And one of them is for your vow and the
others are just free-will. פירשתי מנחה Mincha, של עישרונות ואיני יודע כמה
פירשתי *Perashti mincha shel isaronot ve-eini yodea kama perashti*. If I said
I will bring a מנחה Mincha, *mincha* of x עישרונות *isaronot* and
I don't remember how much the x was. Now this is similar
to the first case in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, but here you
mentioned the word מנחה Mincha, *mincha*. In the first case of the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* you just said x עישרונות *isaronot* and I don't
remember how many. So it seems like it should be the same.
יביא ששים עישרון *Yavi shishim isaron*, and the תנא tanna קמא *Tanna
Kamma* certainly thinks it's the same, bring sixty עישרון *isaron*, and anything
that is x is for your מנחה Mincha, *mincha* and 60 minus
x would be free-will, whatever the x was. רבי Rabbi,
אומר יביא מנחות Menachot, של עישרונות מאחד ועד ששים *Rebbi omer yavi
menachot shel isronot me-echad ve-ad shishim*. No, you have to bring sixty
מנחות Menachot, *menachot* from one of one עישרון *isaron*, one of two,
one of three, one of four, one of five, you have to
bring all types because you cannot just bring sixty all in one
vessel somehow, because if you said x, it can't be more than
x. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is of course going to ask,
well then why doesn't he debate that even in the first case
of the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* when you said
עישרון *isaron*? And maybe he does. But for רבי Rabbi *Rebbi*, it's
not enough to bring more and stipulate, it has to be exactly
the amount in each one in its separate vessel. So therefore you
would have to bring all the options from one to sixty. Let's
take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. פשיטא *Peshita*, so this
is obvious if you say עישרון *isaron* you bring one עישרון *isaron*.
עישרונות יביא שתיים איצטריכא ליה *Isaronot yavi shtayim itztricha lei*. No, the
חידוש chiddush *chiddush* is the second part. If you say in the
plural עישרונות *isaronot*, we're looking at the first part of the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishnah*, then that means a minimum is two. הא נמי פשיטא
מיעוט עישרונות שתיים *Ha nami peshita miyut isaronot shtayim*, that's also obvious,
the minimum of what the plural can mean is two. פירשתי איצטריכא
ליה *Perashti itztricha lei*.
You're right, the first two cases are obvious, but it's to get
us to the third case, which is I said and I don't
know how much. And in that case the חידוש is you bring
sixty and you stipulate. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara is going
to look at that case פירשתי ואינו יודע מה פירשתי pirashti ve-eino
yodea mah pirashti יביא ששים עשרון. yavi shishim isaron. מאן תנא? man
tanna?
Which תנא tanna. says that you can bring sixty and implicitly stipulate?
I mean it's implicit in the משנה. Mishnah אמר חזקיה: amar Chizkiyah:
דלא כרבי. delo ke-Rabbi. That's not like רבי, Rabbi דבי רבי אמר
de-vei Rabbi amar יביא מנחות של עשרונות מאחת ועד ששים. yavi menachot
shel esronot me-achat ve-ad shishim. רבי Rabbi at the end of the
משנה Mishna. says that you can have to bring the exact amount
you said. So he in the first case would also say you
have to bring the exact amount you said and you have to
bring sixty מנחות Menachot from one to sixty.
So the גמרא Gemara says ורבי יוחנן אמר ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar אפילו
תימא רבי. afilu teima Rabbi. No no no. רבי Rabbi could agree
with the first case of the משנה. Mishna, It stands to reason,
right? רבי Rabbi only said his position in the last case of
the משנה. Mishna. What's the difference? אפילו תימא רבי afilu teima Rabbi
באומר פירשתי עשרונות אבל לא כפתי בכלי. be-omer pirashti esronot aval lo
kafiti bi-kli. When you said I will bring X עשרונות esronot and
you didn't say a מנחה Mincha, of X עשרונות, esronot, so you
didn't specify that it all has to be one unit. You didn't
say they all are coming in one vessel. By you're saying a
מנחה Mincha. of X עשרונות esronot it's implicitly one מנחה, Mincha one
vessel, and therefore it has to be the full amount and it
can't be more either than the full amount—it has to be the
exact amount. But when you just say עשרונות, esronot, you know, maybe
that's multiple מנחות Menachot or maybe it's multiple כלים keilim if you
can bring a מנחה Mincha in multiple כלים—not clear, פשט pshat is
that you can't—but maybe it's even multiple מנחות. Menachot So therefore if
you didn't say כלי kli and you didn't say מנחה, Mincha you
just said
עשרונות, esronot, דמייתי ששים עשרון בששים מני. de-maiti shishim isaron be-shishim mani.
So you bring sixty עשרונות, esronot, each one in its separate vessel.
And then you know it's really a question. If you said ten
עשרונות, esronot, maybe that means ten מנחות Menachot each one of one
עשרון. isaron. So you didn't say מנחה Mincha, of ten עשרונות. esronot.
So therefore you can bring all sixty—the ones that are needed for
your vow are for your vow, the rest are a נדבה. nedavah.
But when you say a מנחה Mincha, of X עשרונות esronot or
a—you know—or a—which is a later case where you say עשרונות esronot
in one כלי kli or explicit of that nature, then according to
רבי you have to bring each one separate: one, two, three, four,
five... because you can't—you have to have the exact amount in the
כלי and we'll see a little bit more later why it has
to be the exact amount. Okay but that's רבי's position. Okay. הרי
עלי מנחה יביא איזה שירצה. harei alai mincha yavi eizeh she-yirtzeh. But
first we're going to look before we circle back to that at
the middle case of which type of a מנחה. Mincha So if
you don't specify you can say whichever one—whichever one that you want.
Okay. תנא. tanna: And but then of course that's okay, that's obvious.
But then we get to the more interesting position of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda who says it has to be סולת soleth because it
is the מיוחדת, the designated one or the somehow distinguished one. So
the גמרא's Gemara, going to try to understand what that means. Why
is מנחת סולת soleth. for him the one that you mean if
you don't specify otherwise? So let's take a look.
תנא: Tanna הואיל ופתח בו הכתוב תחילה. ho'il u-fatach bo ha-katuv techilah.
So in the ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position is explained
because it is the first one the תורה Torah opens with. Okay
because here's what it says in ויקרא: Vayikra ונפש כי תקריב—this ve-nefesh
ki takriv is the beginning of פרק ב—קרבן מנחה Mincha לה' סולת
solet, יהיה קרבנו ויצק עליה שמן Shemen, ונתן עליה לבונה. levonah. If
you're bringing a מנחה Mincha, it should be סולת solet with oil
and לבונה. And then there are three פסוקים pesukim about that. And
then it says: וכי תקריב קרבן מנחה מאפה תנור ve-khi takriv korban
mincha ma'afeh tanur if it's מאפה תנור, ma'afeh tanur, ואם מנחה על
המחבת קרבנך. ve-im mincha al ha-machavat korbanekha. So the first one, the
default one, is if you're bringing a מנחה Mincha, it should be
סולת. So that's—it seems like a very reasonable position. But the גמרא
Gemara challenges this. אלא מעתה ela me-ata says the גמרא, Gemara if
that—if based on that: האומר הרי עלי עולה יביא בן בקר הואיל
ופתח בו הכתוב תחילה. ha-omer harei alai olah yavi ben bakar ho'il
u-fatach bo ha-katuv techilah. If you say I'm going to bring an
עולה olah and you don't specify, you should be obligated to bring
from the cattle, you know, a cow or a calf, because it
is the first one in the תורה Torah in the very beginning
of ויקרא Vayikra when it says if you bring an עולה: olah:
אם עולה קרבנו מן הבקר, im olah korbano min ha-bakar, right? זכר
תמים יקריבנו. zachar tamim yakrivennu. So why don't we say that? And
how do we know we don't?
Because—ופתח בו הכתוב תחילה—מן הצאן or similarly if somebody says I'm going
to bring an עולה olah
from the flock, which flock can be sheep or goats, יביא כשב,
yavi keves, you would have to bring a sheep, הואיל ופתח בו
הכתוב תחילה, ho'il u-fatach bo ha-katuv techilah, because similarly the תורה Torah
speaks first about sheep before it speaks about goats. מן העוף, min
ha-of, and if you say I'm going to bring an עולה olah
from birds, יביא תורים, yavi torim, you should have to bring from
the תורים, torim, from the turtle doves,
הואיל ופתח בו הכתוב תחילה, ho'il u-fatach bo ha-katuv techilah, because again
that's mentioned before the בני יונה—בני יונה actually I think are the
turtle doves. Anyway, אלמה תנן? almah tnan? So okay, maybe that's true.
Maybe if you don't specify you have to do the first one
mentioned. But no, the next משנה Mishna. we're about to teach says
the following: הרי עלי עולה, harei alai olah, if somebody just says
I'm obligating myself in an עולה, olah, יביא כשב, yavi keves, bring
a lamb—you don't bring a cow. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר תור
או בן יונה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah omer tor o ben yonah,
you bring one of the birds. And actually the גמרא Gemara is
going to say over there that they really debate similarly that you
bring the minimum, you know, the same way
when you say two the minimum is—when you say
multiple מנחות, Menachot, that's also obvious, the
max—the minimum of what the plural can mean is two. but either
way it is not having to do the first thing mentioned in
the פסוק *pasuk*. So how by a מנחה Mincha. *Mincha* you are
you know you focus on the first thing mentioned in the פסוק
*pasuk*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ולא פליג רבי יהודה הא
*velo palig Rebbe Yehuda ha* and there רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* does
not disagree meaning okay that's the תנא קמא *Tanna Kama* but there's
no רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* who disagrees by the עולה *olah*. So
why if he's based on the first thing in the פסוק *pasuk*
by the מנחה mincha *Mincha* why doesn't he use the same logic
by the עולה *olah*? אלא *Ella* so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* steps
back from this I don't think the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* should be
stepping back from this let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara's* answer
is but I actually think there's a very good logic to distinguish
between those cases but let's first see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara's*
answer is. אלא מאי מיוחדת שבמנחות דלית לה שם לוואי *Ella mai
meyuchedet shebemenachot delait leh shem levai*. What does it mean that it's
distinctive amongst the מנחות Menachot, *menachot*? It means it does not have
a you know a qualifying name an attendant name it's just called
a מנחה mincha *Mincha* you know it's not called a מנחת מחבת
*Minchat Machavat* or מנחת מרחשת *Minchat Marcheshet* right we call it you
know סולת *Solet* מנחת סולת *Minchat Solet* but in the תורה *Torah*
it's just אם קרבן korban מנחה mincha, סולת יהיה קרבנו *im korban
Mincha Solet yihiye korbano* and then you know it says so it's
סולת *Solet* is describing that it's made out of flour but but
by the others it says קרבן korban מנחה mincha מאפה תנור ma'afeh
tanur *Korban Mincha Maafei Tanur* מנחה mincha. על המחבת *Mincha al HaMachavat*
okay מנחת מרחשת *Minchat Marcheshet*. So here it is just straight מנחה
mincha *Mincha* so unspecified means מנחה Mincha, *Mincha* you know it's interesting
right when which types of things need the name and which are
the default? So it's like when you know digital watches first came
out I'm that old you know they were digital watches and everything
else was just a watch right now there are like watches or
there are like analog watches. So which is the default is based
on which is the norm and which one requires the qualification or
the שם לוואי *shem levai* the adjective the descriptive name to say
it is not the standard. So that's why מנחת סולת *Minchat Solet*
is because that is without a a qualifying name no descriptor attached
to it. והתנא האי לא פתח בו הכתוב תחילה *Vehatanna hai lo
patach boh hakatuv techilla* so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay that's
a nice answer but the ברייתא Braita. *Braita* says the reason is
because it's the first one the תורה *Torah* opens with so how
are you saying that the reason is because it is the standard
without any you know describing name descriptive name? הא כתוב תחילה קאמר
*ha katuv techilla ka-amar* that's what the תנא *Tanna* says. הכי קאמר
hachi ka'amar, *Hachi ka-amar* here's what the תנא *Tanna* means. איזה מנחה
minchah. מיוחדת שבמנחות דלית לה שם לוואי זו שפתח בו הכתוב תחילה
*Eizeh Mincha meyuchedet shebemenachot delait leh shem levai zo shepatach boh hakatuv
techilla*. Which is the one that is the default one? The one
that does not have a characteristic name? It's the one that's the
first one in the list in the תורה *Torah*. So the fact
that it's the first in the תורה *Torah* is not why we
say that's what you mean when you say מנחה minchah *Mincha* it's
what we say when you say מנחה minchah. *Mincha* you mean סולת
*Solet* it's because it's the one without the descriptor. But it's saying
which one is that? It's the first one in the תורה *Torah*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says פשיטא מנחת סולת קאמר *pshita Minchat
Solet ka-amar* obviously you said it's a מנחת סולת *Minchat Solet* so
why are you saying it's the first one mentioned in the תורה
*Torah* just say when you say מנחה mincha *Mincha* you mean מנחת
סולת *Minchat Solet* because it has no you know qualifying name no
descriptor attached to it. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says סימנא בעלמא *siman be-alma*
it's just a way to remember it you forgot which one is
the default he's telling you if you ever forget which one is
the default go look it up in the פסוקים *psukim* it's the
first one. Okay but the fact that it's mentioned first is really
not about the reason it's just a way to remember the real
reason is because it is the מנחה mincha *Mincha* that does not
have a descriptor name. Now that's a fine explanation nothing wrong with
that you know reason for that should be the default but I
want to say for a minute that the actual reason that the
תורה *Torah* opens with it is a quite good reason and it's
different from the עולה *olah*. Because if you take a look right
here it says ונפש כי תקריב מנחה mincha קרבן korban מנחה mincha
לה' *venefesh ki takriv Mincha korban Mincha la-Hashem* if you're bringing a
מנחה mincha *Mincha* סולת יהיה קרבנו *Solet yihiye korbano* it tells you
what it should be it should be סולת *Solet*. And then it
says but you know if it's מאפה תנור ma'afeh tanur *Maafei Tanur*
and if it's מרחשת *Marcheshet* but it says if you're bringing a
מנחה mincha, *Mincha* boom it should be סולת *Solet*. That's not the
way the תורה *Torah* introduces the עולה *olah* right? It says you
know it says like this אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן לה' מן
הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן תקריבו את קרבנכם *Adam ki yakriv mikem
korban la-Hashem min habihema min habakar umin hatzon takrivu et korbanchem* it
could be from any of the animals אם עולה קרבנו מן הבקר
*im olah korbano min habakar* if you're going to do it from
the cattle this is what you should do ואם מן
הצאן min ha-tzon *ve-im min hatzon* right ואם מן העוף *ve-im
min ha-of* etcetera etcetera. Okay so there is really you know here
it is very clear thing equally it could be A it could
be B it could be C whereas by the מנחה mincha *Mincha*
just presents it as this is what you mean. Okay so I
really like the reason that רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* explains it's interesting
that the גמרא *Gemara* decides to move on and give another explanation.
Okay so now we move on מנחה mincha מן המנחה *Mincha mina
hamincha* if you say. you know, from a type of מנחה, then
it's one. A type of מנחות, Menachot, it's two. So by רב
פפי, Rav Papi, רב פפא Rav Pappa asked, מיני מנחה מהו? minei
mincha mahu? Let's say you use types of מנחה. When you pluralize
the מנחה to מנחות, Menachot, you mean two. Let's say you pluralize
the word type, types of מנחה מהו, mahu, what do we say
you mean? כיון דאמר מיני Keivan d'amar minei types תרתי קאמר, tarti
ka'amar, so two,
that certainly sounds what it sounds like. ומאי מנחה דכולי מנחות נמי
מנחה קרי להו u'mai mincha d'kulei menachot nami mincha kari lehu דכתיב
וזאת תורת המנחה? d'chtiv v'zot torat hamincha?
When you say מנחה, types of מנחה, you mean the category of
מנחה, because when you're speaking about all the מנחות, Menachot you can
use the singular מנחה, like this is the law of the מנחה,
meaning not a single מנחה, but of the category of מנחה. So
types should mean two and the singular מנחה should not discount that.
או דלמא o dilma כיון דאמר מנחה keivan d'amar mincha חדא מנחה
קאמר, chada mincha ka'amar, or maybe we say, no, since you said
מנחה in the singular,
you mean just one. Okay, if that's true,
ומאי מיני מנחה, u'mai minei mincha, מנחה since you said types in
the plural? הכי קאמר, this is what you mean. ממיני מנחה חדא
מנחה עלי. miminei mincha chada mincha alai.
From the various types of the מנחה, I obligate myself in one.
I will bring from the types of the מנחה, but not two,
not two types, but from among the types. So that's a good
question. Do we follow the types in the plural or the מנחה
in the singular? תא שמע, ta shema, let's try to infer it
from our משנה. Mishna מנחה מין מנחה יביא אחת. mincha min mincha
yavi achat.
If you say מנחה or a type of מנחה, you bring one.
המיני מנחה, haminei mincha, that suggests that so the one cases of
one is every word is in the singular, which would suggest that
if one of the words is in the plural, מיני מנחה minei
mincha
types of מנחה, so המיני מנחה שתים haminei mincha shtayim would sound
like you would bring two. So גמרא says no, you can't prove
that. אימא סיפא, eima seifa, look at the second case. Okay, מנחות
מין מנחות יביא שתים. menachot min menachot yavi shtayim. In
the examples it gives for two, it's only when the word when
you have מנחות Menachot. in the plural. המיני מנחה, haminei mincha, that
would suggest that when the word מנחות menachot, is not pluralized, even
if you said מיני מנחה, minei mincha, המיני מנחה חדא haminei mincha
chada would mean one. אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה, ela meiha leika
l'mishma mina, you can't prove it from the משנה, Mishnah. right? That's
why the question was being asked, because the case wasn't addressed in
the משנה. And exactly this tension: the first cases make it sound
like any use of any plural would be two, but the second
cases make it sound only when the word מנחות menachot, is in
the plural does it mean two. So we don't know what to
do when you say מיני מנחה. minei mincha. תא שמע, ta shema,
so let's try and prove it from this, a ברייתא. Braita. מין
מנחות עלי יביא שתי מנחות ממין אחד. min menachot alai yavi shtei
menachot m'min echad. A type from the type of מנחות menachot on
me, you should bring שתי מנחות ממין אחד. shtei menachot m'min echad.
Now that is good because that was not clear in the משנה.
It stands to reason, okay, but it's the case of the משנה
with being with specifying: a type of מנחות, menachot I obligate myself
in a type of מנחות, menachot you have to bring two but
they have to be of the same type. That's the singular word
use of the word type. הממיני מנחה אחת, hamiminei mincha achat,
that would suggest if you had מיני minei in the plural it
would only bring one מנחה. Now why not? That's not so clear,
okay, but it's really because of the end of the ברייתא. Braita
So the גמרא says דילמא לא, dilma lo, that doesn't prove anything.
המיני מנחה haminei mincha maybe שתי מנחות משני מינים. shtei menachot mishnei
minim. No, just if you use the plural מיני מנחה minei mincha
it would not be the same case as מין מנחות. min menachot.
מין מנחות min menachot is two of the same type. מיני מנחה
minei mincha isn't necessarily one, it could also be two but a
different type of two, two of two different types. והלו תניא הכי,
v'halo tanya hachi, so that's totally reasonable, but now the גמרא, you
know, gives its like kicker. We have an explicit end of the
ברייתא baraita that says exactly this case. והא לא תניא הכי, v'ha
lo tanya hachi, that's not what the ברייסא Braisa teaches. מין מנחות
עלי, min menachot alai,
it says if you say a type of מנחות, menachot יביא שתי
מנחות ממין אחד, yavi shtei menachot m'min echad, what we've already said:
a type of מנחות, Menachos you bring two of the same type.
מיני מנחות עלי, minei menachot alai, if you use plural for both,
types of מנחות menachot I obligate myself in, יביא שתי מנחות משני
מינים, yavi shtei menachot mishnei minim, you bring two from two separate
מינים. minim. Okay, so that sounds like I'm sorry it's not explicitly
our case, but that sounds like only because you pluralized מנחות. menachot.
When it wants to say two of two different types, it gave
the example מיני מנחות. minei menachot. And if מיני מנחה minei mincha
meant two of two different types, it would not have had to
go to the case of מיני מנחות. minei menachot. So the fact
that it goes to מיני מנחות minei menachot for two of two
different types seems very clear that מיני מנחה minei mincha is only
one, not two. So the גמרא says המיני מנחה חדא. haminei mincha
chada. That okay, so that does sound like that. If you want
to get two of two types, you have to say מיני מנחות.
minei menachot. גמרא says no, דילמא הא מני רבי שמעון היא. dilma
ha man Rabbi Shimon hi. Maybe you're right that that is what
it suggests, but maybe because this is going according to... to רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Which רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? דאמר מחצה חלות ומחצה
רקיקין יביא. De-amar mechtza chalot u-mechtza rekikin yavi.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that when you bring a מאפה תנור,
ma'afeh tanur it could be all חלות, chalot all רקיקין, rekikin, or
half and half, or as we'll see later, it could be any
division of the ten between those two types. ומאי מיני מנחה? U-mai
minei mincha? So therefore according to him, if you said מיני מנחה,
minei mincha, it would be two types of one מנחה which is
possible, מאפה תנור Maafe Tanur. that has both חלות chalot and רקיקין.
rekikin. מנחה דאית בה תרי מיני. Mincha de-it be tray minei. That,
that. So you're right. This ברייתא baraita. suggests that if you wanted
two types of two מנחות, menachot you would have to say מיני
מנחות. minei menachot. And מיני מנחה, minei mincha, it sounds like is
only one. But it's only, but maybe that's according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon who has a single מנחה that has two types in
it, and that's how we interpret מיני מנחה. minei mincha. אבל, Aval,
ומאי מיני דאית בה תרתי? u-mai minei de-it be tarta? ורבנן דמחצה
חלות ומחצה רקיקין לא יביא. Ve-rabbanan de-mi-mechtza chalot u-mechtza rekikin lo yavi.
But for the Rabbis who say that it has to be either
all חלות chalot, or all רקיקין, rekikin, you cannot divide it. So
maybe שתי מנחות משני מינים? shtei menachot mishnei minim? Maybe according to
the Rabbis, it would be if you say types of מנחה, since
there is no singular מנחה that has two types, maybe the plural
of the use types means two מנחות, each one of a different
type. So the גמרא does not have the resolution. But what we
do have is clarity in our משנה. When you say מין מנחות,
min menachot, when you say מין מנחות min menachot or מיני מנחות
minei menachot or whatever, then if you say
מין מנחות, min menachot, it's two מנחות of one type, מיני מנחות
minei menachot is two מנחות of two types. And what we don't
know is מין, מיני מנחה min, minei mincha if that is two
types of
two מנחות of two types, or putting רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon aside,
or if it really just means no, from among the types but
only one מנחה. That question of רב פפא Rav Pappa is not
resolved. Okay. So now the גמרא continues. פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי
יביא חמשתן. Perashti ve-eini yodeia ma perashti yavi chamishton. I said it
but I don't know which one, so you bring all five. Okay,
this is not the quantity issue but the type issue.
מאן תנא? Man tanna? Who's the תנא that says that the maximum
that you can be choosing between is five? אמר רבי ירמיה דלא
כרבי שמעון. Amar Rabbi Yirmiya de-lo ke-Rabbi Shimon. Not like the רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon who we just quoted. Because remember רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon has a sixth option. It could be the מאפה תנור mafeh
tanur could be all חלות, chalot, all רקיקין, rekikin, or half and
half. So גמרא says דאי כרבי שמעון, de-ei ke-Rabbi Shimon, because according
to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, כיון דאמר מחצה חלות ומחצה רקיקין יביא,
keivan de-amar mechtza chalot u-mechtza rekikin yavi,
since he says it could be half and half. אי נמי סבר
לה כרבי יהודה דאמר כל המנחות באות עשרה, Ei nami savar leh
ke-Rabbi Yehuda de-amar kol ha-menachot ba'ot asara, even if he were to
only hold like רבי יהודה that there would be ten חלות, chalot,
meaning as opposed to the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that
there are twelve. Let's just work with the assumption of ten חלות,
chalot okay. איקלע ספוקי בארבע סרי מנחות, Iklei sefukei be-arba-asrei menachot,
you could end up to fourteen. Now how could you get fourteen?
Because when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you can do half and
half, he doesn't literally mean half and half. He means you can
divide the number of חלות chalot. in a מאפה תנור between רקיקין
rekikin and חלות. chalot So what are the possibilities? Well
you could have all ten as one. You could have then, and
then you could have all ten as type A. Or you could
have nine, one is type A, nine is type B. Two is
type A, eight is type B. Three is type A, seven is
type B. So that's like those, so just do the math there,
that's ten options, right? And then the last option is all of
them as type A. So you could have all type B or
you could have one, two, three, four, five, six, so that's eleven
possibilities. And eleven plus the other three gets you a total of
fourteen. Okay סולת, מרחשת, מחבת, and within the ten חלות chalot that
are, it can be divided between any distribution of חלות chalot, and
רקיקין rekikin that gets you another eleven and that is fourteen. If
it was רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that had twelve חלות, challot. it
would get you thirteen possibilities. Okay plus three would get you total
sixteen. Okay איקלע ספוקי בארבע סרי מנחות. iklei sefukei be-arba-asrei menachot. אביי
אמר אפילו תימא רבי שמעון. Abaye amar afilu teima Rabbi Shimon.
No,
even according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you only bring these five.
Why? דשמעינן ליה לרבי שמעון דאמר מייתי ומתני. she-shaminun leh le-Rabbi Shimon
de-amar meisi u-masni. Because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says in another context
you can bring and you can stipulate. So let's see what this
means. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. רבי שמעון אומר למחר
מביא אשמו ולוגו עמו. Rabbi Shimon omer le-machar mevi ashamo ve-logo imo.
Okay,
so this is a whole complicated case of somebody who might be
a נזיר, Nazir, might be a מצורע, metzora, might be a מצורע
טהור, metzora tahor, מצורע מוחלט, metzora muchlat, all these different possibilities and
the question is how do you bring the קרבנות korbanot at the
end to cover his bases and that he can become טהור tahor
and get on with his life. Okay, so very complicated but how
does it get reconciled? ואומר, Ve-omer, so here's what it says. Okay
אם מצורע הוא. im metzora hu. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
here's what you do. You bring the לוג log which you need
for the טהרה tahara of the מצורע. metzora. Okay and the אשם
asham which you also need for the טהרה tahara of the מצורע
metzora and you say the following: אם מצורע הוא Im metzora hu
if this guy's a מצורע metzora זהו אשמו וזהו לוגו. zehu ashamo
vezehu logo. This is the this is the אשם asham and the
לוג log and you do you're going to do what you need
to to make him טהור. tahor. ואם לאו Ve'im lav
and if he's not a מצורע metzora אשם זה יהא שלמי נדבה
asham ze yehe shalmei nedava
so this אשם asham should be a שלמים shlamim okay. שלמים shlamim
could be male female whatever it's good and you can make an
אשם asham into a שלמים. shlamim. ואותו אשם טעון שחיטה בצפון. Ve'oto
asham ta'un shechita batzafon.
So now you have two possibilities, it might be an אשם asham
it might be a שלמים shlamim so you have to cover all
your bases. So now what do you do with it? You שחט
shacht it in the north. If it's a שלמים shlamim it's קדשים
קלים kodashim kalim could be שחטed shacht anywhere. If it's an אשם
asham it has to be שחטed shacht in the north, it's קדשי
קדשים. kodshei kodashim. ומתן בהונות Umatan behonot
you put it on you know the you know the the thumb
and the toe and the ears or whatever to purify him. Okay
that's what you do with the blood because it might be an
אשם asham and he might be a מצורע. metzora. וסמיכה Usmicha
you do סמיכה smicha on it because you do סמיכה smicha on
on it if it were a שלמים. shlamim. Now תוספות Tosafot points
out that you actually also do סמיכה smicha on it if it's
an אשם asham but there's a debate whether it is an אשם
asham the סמיכה smicha is דאורייתא de'oraita or not so how exactly
do you do a סמיכה? smicha? Because you're not allowed to do
סמיכה smicha on an animal that you don't have a חיוב chiyuv
to do סמיכה smicha on because it's like you're using קדשים kodashim
so you don't really rest your weight on it and so on.
Okay but the סמיכה smicha is definitely needed for the שלמים. shlamim.
ונסכים Unesachim you do נסכים nesachim because that's what you do for
a שלמים. shlamim. Now really the אשם מצורע asham metzora for those
who were remembering from what we learned a couple weeks ago actually
does have נסכים nesachim that come with it okay but other אשמות
ashamot would not so we're just emphasizing this is going to have
נסכים. nesachim. ותנופת חזה ושוק Utnufat chazeh veshok you wave the חזה
chazeh and the שוק shok which is what you do with a
שלמים shlamim but not with an אשם. asham. So you basically cover
all your bases and it's פסיקא psika to do everything, some of
it is not necessary if it's A or if it's B but
it's not a problem so you just do all the things you
need with it and you're covered. ונאכל לזכרי כהונה ליום ולילה Vene'echal
lezichrei kehuna leyom velaila and it'll be eaten for male כהנים kohanim
for day and night even though if it was a שלמים shlamim
it could be eaten outside the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash by anybody
in ירושלים Yerushalayim for two days. So you're limiting the eaters and
you're limiting the time and that's a reason why we normally don't
like that because it might be a שלמים shlamim and then you're
force you might be forcing it to get burnt before it needs
to if it doesn't get eaten in time. Nevertheless that's what we
do in order to make it possible for this guy to move
on with his life. Okay ליום ולילה. Leyom velaila. Now ואף על
גב דקמפרק מר בשחיטת קדשים Ve'af al gav dekamifrek Mar biShechitat Kodashim
and even though the master meaning the גמרא it's interesting when it's
like self-referencing itself asks when we discuss this position in קדשים Kodashim
אימת דאמר רבי שמעון מייתי ומתני לכתחילה? Eimat de'amar Rabbi Shimon mayti
umatni lechatchila?
When does Rabbi Shimon allow you to bring something and stipulate if
it's an אשם asham this, if it's a שלמים shlamim that and
do all the various things, you know when does he allow you
to do that like לכתחילה lechatchila at the get-go?
לתקוני גברא Letakkunei gavra to help fix this guy because this guy
needs to get on with his life, he can't be a מצורע
metzora his whole life right? He has to get back to being
a normal state. אבל בעלמא דיעבד אין לכתחילה לא Aval be'alma di'avad
in lechatchila lo but בדיעבד bedi'avad you know but but normally we
wouldn't let you go ahead and stipulate maybe this maybe that, you
know and play all the sides, you know we wouldn't, we wouldn't
make those types of stipulations. We're only allowing it now because this
guy's got to stop being a מצורע. metzora. So the גמרא says
yes. Now we haven't yet to say what the stipulation is going
to be in our case but let's first establish that Rabbi Shimon
allows you in a case of doubt to stipulate let it operate
this way, let it operate that way. So we see by this
case of a מצורע metzora he allows you to stipulate let it
operate this way or that way depending on what it is and
even though we say that's only in a special case of a
מצורע metzora because he's got to get back to with his life,
the גמרא says yeah but there was a particular problem there that
needed the special case to allow it. What was the particular problem
that needed the special case? הני מילי גבי שלמים דקממעיט באכילתן דהוו
להו קדשים לבית הפסול. Hanei milei gabei shlamim dekamam'it ba'achilatan dehavu lehu
kodashim leveit hapasul.
So this is what I said, the special problem there is it
might be a שלמים shlamim and now you're saying only כהנים kohanim
can eat it, only for one day, you might get it might
be a שלמים shlamim and now you're going to have it burnt
on the second day because you're going to be treating it like
an אשם. asham. So there because you will be you know not
just doing something extra but risking destroying the קרבן because you're trying
to treat it both ways, there you need a special allowance and
the special allowance is well we have no choice, this guy's got
to stop being a מצורע. metzora. Okay but in general
Rabbi Shimon if there wasn't the problem of limiting the time of
eating Rabbi Shimon would allow you to stipulate in a case of
doubt. אבל מנחות אפילו לכתחילה Aval menachot afilu lechatchila but by a
מנחה nothing is being limited you can why not stipulate לכתחילה? lechatchila?
Now what is the stipulation right? We haven't said that. So so
it's very easy right? According to the חכמים Chachamim you would bring
five מנחות right? סולת מרחשת מחבת and
and חלות. Chalos and רקיקין, Rekikin, the two types of מאפה תנור.
So you'd have ten, let's work with the idea that they're ten,
ten חלות Chalos, and ten רקיקין. Rekikin. So the same for רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you bring the ten and the ten and you
say look, whichever one I said, I don't remember, you know, like
which one I said, but even if I said something that was
a certain mix of the two, if I said חלות, Chalos then
all the חלות Chalos are my נדר Neder and the רקיקין Rekikin
and the other ones are a נדבה, Nedava, a free will. If
I said רקיקין, Rekikin, all the רקיקין Rekikin are my נדר Neder
and the חלות Chalos and all the other ones are a נדבה.
Nedava. If I said some combination, then, you know, X from the
חלות Chalos and Y from the רקיקין Rekikin are my נדר, Neder,
and ten minus X from the חלות Chalos and ten minus Y
from the רקיקין Rekikin are my נדבה. Nedava. So you just mix
and match. So according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you don't need
fourteen, because you can just stipulate it should be divided as is
necessary. Okay, the ones that are for my נדר Neder are for
my נדר, Neder, the ones that are for my נדבה Nedava are
for my נדבה. Nedava. Very good question. So the גמרא says, אמר
ליה רב פפא לאביי. Amar lei Rav Pappa le'Abaye. So פפא Pappa
said to אביי, Abaye, שמעינן לרבי שמעון דאמר מחצה חלות מחצה רקיקין
יביא. Shami'inan l'Rabbi Shimon d'amar mechtza chalos mechtza rekikin yavi. הא קמייתי
איסרון
אחד. Ha kamaisi isaron echad. So actually it's, the גירסא Girsah is,
ולרבי שמעון אמר ליה רב פפא. u'l'Rabbi Shimon amar lei Rav Pappa.
Let's do that again, אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי ולרבי שמעון דאמר
מחצה חלות מחצה רקיקין יביא. Amar lei Rav Pappa le'Abaye u'l'Rabbi Shimon
d'amar mechtza chalos mechtza rekikin yavi.
So let's play this out about making the stipulation. Okay, so according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says it's possible to bring a
mix of חלות Chalos and רקיקין, Rekikin, הא קמייתי איסרון אחד משני
איסרונות ולוג אחד משני לוגים. ha kamaisi isaron echad mishnei isronos velog
echad mishnei lugin. Okay, so effectively what you're doing is you're going
to bring two לוג Log of שמן, Shemen right? Two איסרונות. Isronos.
Right, because there's a לוג Log in an איסרון Isaron of חלות
Chalos, and a לוג Log in an איסרון Isaron of רקיקין. Rekikin.
And you're going to say of these two לוגין, Lugin, one לוג
Log is, you know, of שמן is for my נדר, Neder, and
of these twenty חלות, Chalos these two איסרונות, Isronos, some combination of
them is for my נדר Neder and the rest is just a
free will. That's what you're basically suggesting. You stipulate and you're saying
out of these twenty, the right piece is going to be for
my נדר Neder and the rest is going to be for my
נדבה. Nedava. All right, שמעינן ליה לרבי שמעון דאמר אם הביא איסרון
אחד משני איסרונות ולוג אחד משני לוגים יצא. shami'inan lei l'Rabbi Shimon
d'amar im heivi isaron echad mishnei isronos velog echad mishnei lugin yatza.
Fine. You know what? That actually works. It sounded like it was
going to be a question, but he's saying it actually works. We
know that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is of that opinion, that if
somebody brought two איסרונות Isronos and two לוגים Logim and he said
I'm saying to find half of this for a מנחה, you know,
that you would bring, you know, you could bring from the
whole, you know, the necessary amount out of each one and that's
your נדר Neder and the rest would be a נדבה. Nedava. So
רש"י Rashi says we don't know where he says that, but okay,
that's actually exactly what you're suggesting he would say and that can
work. So what's the problem? So now, so the problem is this
question: מקמץ היכי קמץ? mikmatz heichi kamitz?
How do you do the קמיצה? kmitza? Okay, so he says I
got you, right? You don't have to bring fourteen מנחות for רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you just bring the same five and you've got
the ten חלות Chalos of חלות Chalos, and the ten of רקיקין
Rekikin and you stipulate and whichever, you know, amount of each one
is needed for your נדר Neder is your נדר, Neder, the rest
is for your נדבה. Nedava. That's exactly, we know רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says you can do that. If you say I'm going to
bring half as a נדר, Neder, then you can say, okay, whichever
half is my נדר Neder and the other half is נדבה. Nedava.
We know he says that you can, you know, we know he
says that you can do that. But how do you take the
קמיצה? kmitza? Because here's the problem. If it's all חלות, Chalos. then
the קמיצה kmitza has to be all out of חלות. Chalos If
it's all רקיקין, Rekikin, then the קמיצה kmitza has to be out
of all רקיקין. Rekikin. If it is a mix of חלות Chalos
and רקיקין, Rekikin, presumably you have to have a קמיצה kmitza that
has the right proportion of חלות Chalos and רקיקין, Rekikin, or at
least it has to have some חלות Chalos, and רקיקין, Rekikin, presumably.
So how can you do it? Right? That, how can you take
a קמיצה? kmitza? You'll take two קמצים. kmatzim. Okay, what are you
going to take? One out of all חלות, Chalos, one out of
all רקיקין, Rekikin, but maybe it was a mix. And so how's
this going to work? מקמץ היכי קמץ? mikmatz heichi kamitz? So דמתני
ואמר. demasni ve'amar. It would work like this.
דמתני ואמר אי חלות לחודייהו ורקיקין לחודייהו אמרי דקא קמצנא מחלות להוי
חלות ודקא קמצנא מרקיקין להוי רקיקין. demasni ve'amar ei chalos lachudaihu verekikin
lachudaihu amri deka kamatzna michalos lihavei chalos vedeka kamatzna merekikin lihavei rekikin.
If I said all חלות, Chalos so you take one קמיצה kmitza
of חלות Chalos, and one of
רקיקין, Rekikin, right, because you have ten of each and they're in
like, and they're separate. And you say if I said all חלות,
Chalos great, the one of חלות Chalos is my נדר, Neder, the
one of רקיקין Rekikin is my נדבה. Nedava. If I said all
רקיקין, Rekikin, the one of רקיקין Rekikin is my נדר, Neder, the
one of חלות Chalos, is my נדבה. Nedava. That we got. What
about if it's a mix?
אי מחצה רקיקין ומחצה חלות אמרי, ei mechtza rekikin umechtza chalos amri,
but if I said half and half, and now it's not just
half and half as we've been learning, it's any possible permutation. So
דקא קמצנא מחלות להוי אמר מחצה חלות ומחצה רקיקין. deka kamatzna michalos
lihavei amar mechtza chalos umechtza rekikin. That קמיצה kmitza I took from
the חלות, Chalos let it work for the half of the חלות
Chalos and half of the whatever the right proportion is, the X
of the חלות chalot and the Y of the רקיקין Rekikin that
was for my
נדר. Neder. my נדר, neder, להוי אמחצה רקיקין ומחצה חלה, lehevei a-mechtzah
rekikin u-mechtzah challah, let that be on the 10-x and the 10-y.
So basically you're just taking two קמץ קמצים, kmatz kmatzim, חלות chalot,
and רקיקין, rekikin, and basically you're saying if it's all חלות, chalot
the חלות chalot work for the חלות chalot and the רקיקין rekikin
work for the רקיקין. rekikin. If it's all רקיקין, rekikin, the same.
If it's a mix, each one, the חלות chalot works for the
right mix of חלות chalot and רקיקין rekikin and the and the
רקיקין rekikin works for the other mix, the non-נדר neder mix of
the חלות chalot and the רקיקין, rekikin, which means that your קמיצה
kmitzah does not have to have both parts of the קרבן in
it. Okay, so let's see. See this. והבא אי מקמץ חד חד
קומץ מחלות ומרקיקין, v'habayey mik'matz chad chad kmatz me-chalot u-me-rekikin, but that's
not going to work because presumably your קמיצה, kmitzah, if your קרבן
is a mix of חלות chalot and רקיקין, rekikin, your קמיצה kmitzah
has to have חלות chalot, and רקיקין rekikin in it. וקא קמיץ
מחלות ארקיקין ומרקיקין אחלות, ve-ka kamitz me-chalot arekikin u-me-rekikin achalot, and that's
not going to work. You're taking two קמיצים, kmitzim, קמצים, kmatzim, one
all חלות, chalot one all רקיקין, rekikin, and you want in the
case that it might be a mix for the חלות chalot to
work on both types and for the רקיקין rekikin to work on
both types. שמיע ליה לרבי שמעון דאמר אם קמץ בידו מאחד על
שניהם יצא. shmina milay r'shimon d'amar im kamatz b'yado me-chad al shenei-hem
yatza. Ah, but you know what? Everything looks like it's going to
be a question, but he's actually saying, actually, this can work. Okay,
because we actually know that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says in a
different context that if you did קמיצה kmitzah from one of the
two, even if you had a mix of חלות chalot and רקיקין
rekikin and your קמיצה kmitzah was just of one of the מינים,
minim, it works for the whole
מנחה. So far, so good. Really, we thought all of these were
going to be problems, but actually they're very consistent with רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. So we just to pause and say where we are.
We started by saying according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it could
be any mix of חלות chalot and רקיקין, rekikin, if you don't
know what you brought, you needed 14 options, you know, the normal
three plus 11 out of the possible permutations of חלות chalot and
רקיקין. rekikin. But then we said no, you can bring all חלות
chalot, and all רקיקין rekikin and you can stipulate and say whichever
mix is right for my נדר neder is my נדר neder and
the rest is for my נדבה. nedavah. And we know רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says you're allowed to stipulate. Okay, and we know רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you're allowed to bring a large thing and
make that exact stipulation. The part like you're allowed to bring two
עשרונות isronot and say the part needed for my נדר neder is
נדר, neder, the part for my נדבה nedavah is נדבה. nedavah. How
about the fact of the קמיצה? kmitzah? That also works. We know
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that even if you take just
from חלות, chalot, it works on the חלות, chalot the mix of
חלות chalot. and רקיקין. rekikin. Just from the רקיקין, rekikin, it works
on a mix of רקיקין rekikin and חלות. chalot, Okay, so you
take one קומץ kmitz חלות, chalot one on one on
one on the רקיקין, rekikin, either they all work for their separate
מין min or they all work for their different types of mixtures
that, you know, based on what your נדר neder is and your
נדבה nedavah is. All right, so that's all going to work. Okay,
but is there a but somewhere here? Okay, but let's—here's the but.
Okay, he says like this. והא
איכא מותר שמן. v'ha ikka motzar shemen. But how about the remainder
of the oil? ואי מחצה חלות ומחצה רקיקין אמר, v'ee mechtzah chalot
u-mechtzah rekikin amar, if you had said some mix of חלות chalot.
and רקיקין, rekikin, מותר שמן מחזירו לחלות. motzar shemen machziru lachaloat. The
remainder of the oil you put back into the חלות. chalot What
does this mean? That if a מנחה is half חלות chalot and
half רקיקין, rekikin, so the חלות chalot, get mixed directly with oil
and they use a lot of oil. The רקיקין rekikin is basically,
you know, a smear of oil and not a heavy use of
the oil. So if it is all חלות, chalot the חלות chalot.
are mixed with their oil. If it's all רקיקין, rekikin, the רקיקין
rekikin get a smear and the rest of the oil is separate.
Okay, is—the כהנים kohanim. eat it, doesn't get mixed directly in the
מנחה. But if it's half and half, any part of the oil
that you did not use, the half of the oil that you
did not use on the רקיקין, rekikin, you go back and you
pour onto the חלות. chalot. And now we've got a problem, right?
Because מותר שמן מחזירו לחלות, motzar shemen machziru lachaloat, if it's half
and half, the remainder of the oil from the רקיקין rekikin goes
back on the חלות. chalot But if it's all one and all
the other, then the remainder of the oil for the רקיקין rekikin
stays separate. אי כולו רקיקין אמר, ee kulo rekikin amar, so if
you had said all רקיקין, rekikin, so then מותר שמן נאכל לכהנים.
motzar shemen ne'echal l'kohanim. Then, then you know, then the רקיקין rekikin
are your נדר, neder, the חלות chalot. are your נדבה, nedavah, they're
separate, and the remainder of the oil—so how are you going to
solve this for רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Right, because how are you
going to know what to do with the oil? You can't go
ahead and if it's all one or all the other, the rest
of the oil for the רקיקין rekikin stays separate, but if they
are it's a half and half, you need to pour it back
into the חלות. chalot, So how you're going to be able to
stipulate? You're not going to know what to do with the oil.
So the גמרא says כרבי שמעון בן יהודה. k'r'shimon ben yehuda. No,
this would follow רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda's position.
דתניא רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון, d'tanya Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda said in the name of רבי שמעון—so Rabbi Shimon this
is with a version of רבי שמעון—that Rabbi Shimon even when you
have them half and half, מושחן כמינו ומותר שמן נאכל לכהנים, moshcham
k'minchu, u-motzar shemen ne'echal l'kohanim, that even when it's half and half,
you do not take the remainder of the oil for the רקיקין
rekikin and pour it back. The remainder of the oil you use
the oil to make like an X, like a Greek chi, xi,
whatever, and it is eaten by the כהנים. kohanim, So according to
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון יהודה Rabbi Shimon Yehuda in the
name of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, whether they are separate and then,
you know, in which case you use all the oil for the
חלות, chalot you do a smear for the רקיקין rekiqin and the
rest is eaten for the כהנים, kohanim, or whether they're mixed, even
when they're mixed, the part the oil that's designated for the רקיקין,
rekiqin, the amount that's not used does not go back to the
חלות chalot but stays separate. So it's perfect, doesn't change at all
whether it's mixed or separate, you have you bring your חלות chalot
with all the oil mixed in, you bring your רקיקין rekiqin with
the little with the little smear and the rest is there for
the כהנים, and you stipulate. And if they're separate קרבנות korbanot they're
separate, if it's some mix of חלות רקיקין, rekiqin, the same would
be done, no different treatment of the oil even if they are
mixed. Okay, so we now have beautifully explained how according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, even though he's got all these other possibilities of,
you know, permutations, it can all work with the right stipulation. It
can work that the קמיצה kmitza doesn't have to be a mix
of both. It can work because the oil doesn't get treated differently
if it's separate, if it's combined, so it all works. All right,
let's just finish up here like to the two dots. אמר ליה
רב כהנא לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Kahana l'Rav Ashi, so רב
כהנא Rav Kahana said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ואיכא לספוקי במנחת
נסכים. v'ika l'ispukei b'minchas nesachim. Okay, so now we're done, we're done
with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and we understand why there are five
options even according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, not fourteen, because with
you bring these two and you stipulate. But he says but there's
a sixth option. The sixth option is you can bring a מנחת
נסכים minchas nesachim like you would bring with the, you know, animals,
and we've learned that you can dedicate that type of a מנחה
separate from the animal, and that would have a different proportion of
oil to flour and so on. דאמר רבא משתנדב אדם מנחת נסכים
בכל יום. de'amar Rava misnadiv adam minchas nesachim b'chol yom. You can
actually make a נדבה nedava of a מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim not
connected to the animal, not just accompanying the animal sacrifices, and that's
different from these five מנחות that are in the first פרק of
ויקרא Vayikra. or the first פרשה parsha of ויקרא. So why why
isn't that a possibility of being considered as one of the things
you have to do to play it safe? So the גמרא says
no, that's character that's categorically different from standard מנחות. כי קא מסתפקא
ליה, ki ka mistafqa lei, when is there a doubt what you
might have meant when you said a type of מנחה but you
don't remember which type? בבאה ביחיד, בבאה בציבור לא מסתפקא ליה. b'ba'ah
b'yachid, b'ba'ah b'tzibur lo mistafqa lei.
Only a type of מנחה that is brought by private
individuals, so a מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim can even be brought by
the
ציבור. tzibur. So normal מנחות are not brought by the ציבור, tzibur,
but a מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim is. So you wouldn't be considering
to do a type of מנחה now it's also brought by an
individual, but you wouldn't be considering it's of a different type. So
that's very different and wouldn't have been one of the ones you
were considering. Here come the better reasons why it would be different.
כי קא מסתפקא ליה בבאה בפני עצמה, בבאה עם הזבח לא מסתפקא
ליה. ki ka mistafqa lei b'ba'ah b'fnei atzma, b'ba'ah im hazevach lo
mistafqa lei. When you have a doubt what you meant, you probably
meant a מנחה that normally comes by itself. A מנחת נסכים, minchas
nesachim, even if there's a חידוש that you can bring it without
the animal, its standard is to come with the animal. So that's
probably not what you had in mind. כי קא מסתפקא ליה, ki
ka mistafqa lei, when do you have a doubt what you might
have meant, טעונה לבונה, te'una levona, with one that comes with frankincense,
again a standard מנחה, שאינה טעונה לבונה לא מסתפקא ליה, she'eina te'una
levona lo mistafqa lei, not one like this, מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim
is so different that unless you said it explicitly we do not
think and remember saying it, we do not think that that was
what you had what you might have said. כי קא מסתפקא ליה,
ki ka mistafqa lei, another one, באה בלוג, ba'ah b'log, one that
comes with every עשרון, issaron, one לוג log of oil, באה בשלשה
לוגין לא מסתפקא ליה, ba'ah b'shlosha login lo mistafqa lei, but you
know, a מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim is like one עשרון issaron to
three לוג log or to two לוג, log, it's a much much
more oil and that is not so so different from a standard
מנחה that unless you remember having said it we do not assume
you might have said it. כי קא מסתפקא ליה, ki ka mistafqa
lei, last difference, טעונה קמיצה, te'una kmitza,
a standard מנחה you do קמיצה, kmitza, שאינה טעונה קמיצה, she'eina te'una
kmitza, מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim you just burn all of it, לא
קא מסתפקא ליה. lo ka mistafqa lei. So that's why it is
not. So when you don't remember what type, you mean one of
the standard five types, you don't mean מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, and
even within רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says that on those five
you can have eleven or of מאפה תנור you can have eleven
permutations, you still can bring the five types and stipulate and do
the קמיצה kmitza in a way and the oil in a way
that is going to work for all the permutations. Okay, we will
end here.